בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is מ"ה, mem-hei, we pick
up on the middle of מ"ד mem-dalet עמוד ב, amud bet,
the two dots, בכל יום היה חוטא. Bechol yom haya choteh. So
we have, we're discussing now the getting of the hot coals from
the top of the altar, which is then going to after
the וידוי viduy and the שחיטה shechita of his cow, ox, excuse
me, and then we're going to obviously now in the process of
talking about the bringing of the קטורת. ketoret. So just to remind
you yesterday, we had a whole important discussion about the idea of
having to vacate the אולם ulam and the היכל heichal and even
the space between the אולם ulam and the היכל heichal when he
is bringing the קטורת, ketoret, and we broadened that to number one,
לכפר בקודש, l'chaper bakodesh, any of the עבודות avodos he does on
the inside including the blood of the ox and of the goat.
And not only that, but we even broadened it outside of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur when other types of כפרה בקודש kapara bakodesh are
being done, maybe even when the daily קטורת ketoret is being done,
which was a bit of a shocker, and that was not fully
sort of elaborated on, that idea of the daily קטורת. ketoret. Maybe
it was only meant the regular קטורת ketoret but done on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. But anyway, the idea of vacating that space in
a variety of cases, particularly all the עבודות פנים, avodos pnim, all
the עבודות avodos in the היכל heichal that are done on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so now back to the shoveling of the
coals. בכל יום היה חוטא, Bechol yom haya choteh, every day he
would shovel בשל כסף beshel kesef with the silver one and ומערה
לתוך של זהב ume'ara letoch shel zahav and poured into a gold,
and today he would shovel directly with a gold one. The גמרא
Gemara says, מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What is the reason that normally
you would do it with two? התורה חסה על ממונם של ישראל,
HaTorah chasa al mamonam shel Yisrael, the Torah is concerned with the
waste of Jewish money. So yes, you had all these beautiful vessels
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we got a bizarre application of
that before that they wanted to have a wood box when everything
else was gold and silver. But here at least the point is
yes, have gold, have silver, but don't waste it. So if you
shovel with gold, gold is a very soft metal and you shovel
in the coals, that'll be a waste. So shovel with the silver
and pour it into the
gold. והיום חוטא בשל זהב ובה היה מכניס. Vehayom choteh beshel zahav
uva haya machnis. Today he would use only gold. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? Why? משום חולשת כהן גדול, mishum chulshat Kohen Gadol, the weakness
of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. You don't want to be just
doing a lot of manipulation and you want to streamline things and
so on. I pointed out to you already that the רש"ש Rashash
says that there seems to be a more straightforward reason because the
simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is that the same thing you
shovel the coals is the one you bring into the קודש קודשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. And he explains the גמרא Gemara again back to another
sort of question in the משנה Mishna that maybe when it says
about what was special today, it's not limiting itself to for some
of this discussion, particularly around the coals and how they were shoveled,
maybe it's not limiting itself to just the קטורת ketoret of the
קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, but maybe it's talking even on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur they would do this special for the other קטורות ketores
that was done morning and afternoon, and maybe that's why it gives
this reason. So that's two interesting points. One is, is there based
on the פסוקים pesukim maybe there's an idea of going straight from
the shoveling on the altar to the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, not
to do a switching, maybe that's even based on the פסוקים pesukim
not just the side concern about the sort of burden on the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And the other question, again, we and רש"י
Rashi particularly emphasizes that the משנה Mishna when it's talking about special
means specifically special for the קטורת ketoret of the קודש קודשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, but is it possible to read the משנה Mishna a little
broader? That everything special was done today even by the other קטורות
ketores as well, at least certain aspects.
But how do you know they don't use just one shovel
for the rest of the year?
Is that what was tradition? I mean, what do you mean? Well,
because you actually want to bring it in
in a golden one because it's nicer? Yeah. But then you still
use one because of the waste of the gold. Okay. בכל יום
בשל ארבעה
קבין, Bechol yom beshel arba'a kabin, every normal day you shovel with
four and pour into three, but today since you're using only one,
you shovel with the three that you're going to use, the one
that holds three קב. kav. תנא, Tana, we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, נתפזרו לו קב גחלים. Nitpazru lo kav gechalim. So this is
the issue about where you would do the pouring. Right? Michael asked
if the pouring done on the top of the altar, and I
said it sounds like elsewhere that it's done on the floor. And
this is based on this, because it says when the coals, if
the coals scattered, that extra when you go from four to three,
מכבדן לאמה, Mechabdan l'ama, you sweep them into the אמה, ama, which
was this trench in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash with water going
through. It's sort of like you know the whole thing they have
in Israel about how they mop the floors and they have a
hole in the floor, whatever, you know, so they already, so there's
a good מסורה mesorah to that all the way to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You'd mop everything into this trench with water and
it would take everything out. I don't know exactly where in the
עזרה azara it was. But anyway, so here you would sweep the
coals into that trench as well, which certainly if pretty clear that
the pouring was done on the floor so you would come down
with the ארבעה קבין arba'a kabin off the altar and then you
would do the switch on the floor. Certainly what it sounds like.
And if there's extra you would sweep it. That's on a normal
day. תני חדא קב, Tani chada kav, so one ברייתא braita teaches
there would be an extra קב kav which is based on our
משנה Mishna from four to three. ותני אידך, Vetani idach, you have
another ברייתא, braita, קביים, kabbayim, two קבין kabin would be
extra. בשלמא הך דתני קב, Bishlama hach detani kav, I get the
position that there would be an extra קב kav when you did
the switch, רבנן. Rabbanan. That's the Rabbis who said you would go
from four to three. Now there was another position in the משנה
Mishnah that said you went from six to
three. Right, but how do you get that would be three extra?
But how do you get the position that there were two
extra? אלא הא דתני קביים, Ella ha de-tani kabayim, that it says
there were two extra that would scatter, מני, mani, who is it?
לא רבנן ולא רבי יוסי, Lo Rabbanan ve-lo Rabbi Yosi, it's not
Rabbanan who says it was four to three, and not Rabbi Yosi
who says six to three. So אמר רב שיזבי אמר רבי ישמעאל
בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה. Amar Rav Shizbi amar Rabbi Yishmael
beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. It's Rabbi Yishmael the son of
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. So we have all positions: four, five, and
six. דתניא, De-tanya, רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר,
Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer, בשל קביים היה
מכניס. be-shel kabayim hayah machnis.
So he says that actually, excuse me, it wasn't four, five, and
six. Yes, you shoveled, he says you shoveled with six, okay, like
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, but he says you did not pour it
into something that held three—I'm sorry, I got that wrong. You shoveled
with, you shoveled with four like the רבנן, Rabbanan, but you didn't
pour it into something that held three, you poured it into something
that only held two. Okay, so in our משנה, Mishnah, everybody agreed
that the מחתה, machtah, the fire pan you would bring in, this
is a normal day, held three קב, kab, and the debate was,
did the original one you shoveled off of the מזבח mizbe'ach four
or six, which would lead to a difference of one or three.
The ברייתא braitah that says two is an opinion that yes, you
shoveled with four, but you poured it into one not that held
three, but one that held two, and therefore you had two extra
that scattered.
It sounds like if it accidentally spilled, but here, no, it had
to spill.
You were going from more to less, not accidentally. Okay, רב אשי
אמר,
Rav
Ashi amar,
but the question is, what was the difference? Okay, so now we
have not only a difference between how much the initial shovel was,
three or six, but four or six, but a question how much
the shovel you carried in was, was it three or was it
two.
I don't know, I mean you want more so that when you
do the transfer you get enough in, but why such a large
gap I don't know. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, אפילו תימא
רבי יוסי, Afilu tema Rabbi Yosi, it could even be רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi that says six and you went from a six to
three. So if you went from six to three, how is it
that only two extra? והכי קאמר, Ve-hachi ka'amar, here's how. בכל יום
היה חוטף בשל סאה מדברית ומערה לתוך שלש קבין ירושלמיות. Be-chol yom
hayah chotev be-shel se'ah midbarit u-me'arah le-toch shalosh kabin Yerushalmiyot.
So there was actually a difference of the of the measures. You
know, how much were the measures indicated when they were in the
wilderness, and then when they got to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, there
was a change in what the measure signified and the same measure
actually was included, you know, was larger. The same unit was used
for a larger amount. So a
סאה, se'ah, six of the of the old measures is really only
going to be five of the new measures. So they would dig,
right, they added a sixth. So you would dig it with one
that had six, but six old measures, which really means five new
ones, and you pour it into three, something that had three new
ones, so the difference would be two, five. Anyway, that was the
normal year where you went from you shoveled a lot with silver
and you poured it into less of gold. ובכל יום הייתה כבדה
והיום קלה. U-ve-chol yom hayetah kevedah ve-hayom kalah. Normally it would be
a heavy metal, presumably even the gold one that you would bring
in, now it would be light, a thinner gold and also with
a longer arm. And we're going to talk later about the whole
idea of the manipulation. תניא ותנא ברייתא, Tanya ve-tana braitah, ובכל יום
הייתה גלדה עבה והיום רכה. U-ve-chol yom hayetah guldah avah ve-hayom rakah.
Normally the גלדה, guldah, not the gold, but sort of the thickness,
the wall would be thick and today it would be thin. ובכל
יום הייתה קצרה והיום ארוכה. U-ve-chol yom hayetah ketzarah ve-hayom arucha. Normally
the handle would be short, today long. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why?
כדי שתהא זרועו של כהן גדול מסייעתו. Kedei she-tehei zero'o shel Kohen
Gadol mesaya'ato.
It would be a longer handle and thinner because so you could
use your arm and your elbow in order to manipulate it, thank
you so much, as we will see when we get to discussing
how the קטורת ketoret was actually put on, but you're holding things
in both hands and you have to pour into both hands from
the from the incense, so you're going to need to be using,
manipulating with your arms and elbows. Now תניא ותנא ברייתא, Tanya ve-tana
braitah, בכל יום לא היה לה ניאשתי והיום
היה לה ניאשתי, Be-chol yom lo hayah lah niashti ve-hayom hayah lah
niashti, דברי בן הסגן. divrei Ben Ha-Segan.
That's what the son of the סגן Segan says. Always interesting when
you have the סגן, Segan, which we've had a couple times, commenting
on this, the vice-כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. What is this ניאשתי? niashti?
So talk about, you know, an opportunity to try to figure something
out completely from context. Like what is this, what could you imagine
it could be? I mean maybe we have parallels, but it's one
of those words where we really don't have a parallel to it.
So what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi speculates, or רש"י Rashi
says, here's what רש"י Rashi says, two lines down the wide lines.
טבעת בראשה. Taba'at be-roshah.
It would have some type of a of a ring שמקשקש ומשמיע
קול. she-mekashkesh u-mashmi'a kol. So then when you're walking with it, it
bangs the metal, bangs, you know, the ring bangs against the metal
of the pan and it makes a sign, it makes a sound.
משום ונשמע קולו בבואו, Mishum ve-nishma kolo be-vo'o, like the idea that
when you go into the קודש, Kodesh, you should be—now that's why
he normally wears the מעיל. me'il. So it's quite a fascinating רש"י
Rashi because why, because why wouldn't that work today? Because today he's
only wearing בגדי לבן. bigdei lavan. So רש"י Rashi has the fascinating
idea, in general the מעיל me'il has the pomegranates and the bells
at the bottom, some idea of making a sound as you enter
into the היכל. heichal. We've read that a bunch of times, right?
But you don't have that now, you're all in בגדי לבן. bigdei
lavan. Because why? Why wouldn't that work today? Today he's only wearing
בגדי לבן. Bigdei Lavan. So רש״י Rashi has the fascinating idea, there's
in general the מעיל Me'il has the pomegranates and the bells at
the bottom. There's some idea of making a sound as you enter
into the היכל. Heichal. Right, go in a bunch of times, not
just the... Right. But you don't have that now, you're all in
בגדי לבן. Bigdei Lavan. So you don't have this sound that you
make when you enter in. So רש״י Rashi seems that at least
when you're bringing in the fire pan, that's not the only thing
you would do there, but at least we would have some קיום
Kiyum of that idea. It's quite fascinating, the importance of what that
idea might be. Just one second. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot
says בכל יום לא היה לה נרתיק. Bechol yom lo haya la
nartik. So
תוספות Tosafot says he quotes רש״י Rashi and then two lines down
he says ובירושלמי גרסינן נרתיק. U'viyerushalmi garsinan nartik. נרתיק Nartik is like
a sheath. שלא יכוה, Shelo yichaveh,
you should not burn. ונראה לי לריב״א כעין נרתיק של עור היה
עשוי סביב ידה. V'nireh li l'Riva k'ein nartik shel or haya asui
saviv yada. You would have a pot handle. You would have a
leather handle to go around the around the you know the handle,
like a pot holder. You'd have you know
you have all these coals and you have this metal and you're
holding it. How is it that you don't burn? Now the question
is okay that's wonderful. Why didn't you have it during the rest
of the year? So I thought the reason you would that you
would have it only now is because the gold was thinner. So
I don't know, but my sense is if you have a thicker
metal, is that wrong or right? If you have a thicker metal
and you have something hot, will it take longer for the for
the heat to transfer to be conduct and transfer to the extremities
of it? I thought maybe has to do with the fact that
the metal was thinner. Of course also the handle was longer, so
that might have made it not such a problem. So תוספות Tosafot
would say no. The issue was was that you're gonna have to
hours later or however much long later, go back and get the
fire pan that had been burning with the קטורת Ketoret and retrieve
it. Right, so the now that you're bringing it in that's not
a problem, in a short period of time it's not going to
get so hot, the metal. But then you're going to put the
קטורת Ketoret on, go do the other עבודות, Avodot, come back and
retrieve it and it still has hot coals in it and now
by now the handle is hot. So that's why you needed to
have this leather pot holder essentially handle on it.
מצוות היום במחתות הפנימיות, Mitzvat hayom b'machtot hapnimiyot, those are probably the
really really hot ones because the heat doesn't expire.
Maybe. Maybe. But I think תוספות Tosafot explanation is better even that
wouldn't so much explain this degree of difference. Okay, so back to
the גמרא. Gemara. Five lines from the bottom. בכל יום הייתה זהב
ירוק. Bechol yom hayta zahav yarok.
Normally it would be a green but probably yellow gold and today
a red gold. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, because as we
pointed out ירוק yarok in the משנה Mishnah could mean gold could
mean green or red green or yellow. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav
Chisda, שבעה זהבים הם. Shiva zehavim hem. There are seven types of
gold: זהב, Zahav, normal gold, זהב טוב, Zahav tov, good gold, וזהב
אופיר, v'Zahav Ofir, gold from אופיר, Ofir, וזהב מופז, v'Zahav mufaz, וזהב
שחוט, v'Zahav shachut, וזהב סגור, v'Zahav sagur, וזהב פרווים. v'Zahav parvayim.
So let's say what each one means. זהב וזהב טוב, Zahav v'Zahav
tov, normal gold and good gold, דכתיב dechtiv the verse says וזהב
הארץ ההיא טוב, v'zahav ha'aretz hahi tov, right in the beginning of
בראשית. Bereishit. So that gold was good, meaning that there is סתם
stam gold and then there's good gold. Okay, so but there's higher
quality. זהב אופיר, Zahav Ofir, so what's זהב אופיר? Zahav Ofir? דאתי
מאופיר. D'ati me'Ofir.
It comes from the land of אופיר Ofir but presumably it's of
some different quality. I had no idea and I did not look
up. I'm sure I a quick search in Wikipedia could give information
meaning I know that gold as a pure element obviously only comes
in one form, but I imagine gold as it's found in the
real world has probably what like different degrees of impurities
and different
whatever so it comes of
different qualities. Pure gold might be very soft I'm not sure. Right,
that's certainly true
right
you can't yeah pure gold is is too malleable I think for
most uses, right. Okay, זהב מופז, Zahav mufaz, what's זהב מופז? Zahav
mufaz?
שדומה לפז. Shedomeh l'paz. It's similar to פז. paz. Now פז paz
I always thought was gold right. So רש״י Rashi says פז paz
is מצהיב כמרגלית. matzhiv k'margalit. It shines like a type of a
precious stone. So apparently that's but aren't there פסוקים pesukim it says
which have פז paz to I thought meant
gold? Anyway okay I have to check it out. זהב שחוט, Zahav
shachut, now literally slaughtered or it might from the word חוט chut
like a string, שנטווה כחוט, she'nitva k'chut, that it is like you
know it's very you make it you you comb it like a
string. Basically gold made into gold gold string. But that's not a
different type of a gold right. So רש״י Rashi says that it's
so soft it can be made into a string, that it that
it's able to be processed that way. זהב סגור, Zahav sagur, so
what's closed gold? בשעה שנפתח כל החנויות נסגרו. Besha'ah sheniftach kol hachanuyot
nisgaru. When this gold comes on the market all the other gold
stores close up. This clearly is of such a great quality. זהב
פרווים Zahav parvayim and this is why we're mentioning all of this,
שדומה לדם הפרים. shedomeh l'dam haparim. That's red gold which is like
the blood of of oxen and therefore and that is the gold
that he would use. So of course it seems to be... You
know, significant here, what is the significance of the red gold? We
never point it out. Well maybe it's just that it's more expensive,
it's different, it's fancy. But maybe also because it evokes blood. So
remember the קטורת, Ketoret, we're bringing in the קטורת, Ketoret, but the
other thing that you're going to be doing here that parallel the
קטורת Ketoret are the bringing in of the blood, the blood of
the ox, the blood of the goat and we mentioned before an
interesting idea that normally we think these are very different processes, the
קטורת Ketoret as I mentioned the other day is more about that
encounter with God, you know בזאת יבוא אהרן אל הקדש, Bezot yavo
Aharon el hakodesh, whereas the blood is more about cleansing the המקדש.
Hamikdash. But the גמרא Gemara connected them and said that the קטורת
Ketoret is מכפר Mechaper and the גמרא Gemara said that when you
do whether the קטורת Ketoret or the blood you have to exit
you have to vacate the היכל Heichal בבואו לכפר בקדש. bevo'o l'chaper
bakodesh.
So now that they're linked to this idea of לכפר, l'chaper, it's
interesting that we're making the gold here a red gold which evokes
the idea of the blood, שדומה לדם הפרים. she'domeh l'dam haparin.
Is it more expensive or just rare?
Presumably. רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר amar חמישה הן. chamisha hen. No,
no, no, there are not seven, there are only five. וכל חד
וחד אית ביה זהבא וזהבא טבא. V'chol chad v'chad it bei zahava
v'zahava tava. All of those five which are identifying the categories have
a different mix of normal gold and good gold. So maybe plus
other things or maybe the whole difference is the proportions of those
two. But presumably plus other things. Alright, תניא נמי הכי tanya nami
hachi we saw this in the ברייתא, Beraita, בכל יום היה זהבו
ירוק והיום אדום. bechol yom hayah zehavo yarok v'hayom adom. Every day
it was yellow, today red. והיינו זהב פרווים v'hainu zahav parvayim and
that is the gold of Parvayim שדומה לדם הפרים. she'domeh l'dam haparin.
So then it's similar to the blood of the ox. And so
here the ברייתא Beraita explicitly identifies the red gold as gold that
is similar to the blood of ox. This character of gold which
I think is important in terms of linking the קטורת Ketoret to
the idea of the כפרה kaparah of the blood. Okay. בכל יום
היה מקריב פרס שחרית פרס בין הערביים. bechol yom hayah makriv pras
shacharit pras bein ha'arbayim. Normally it would be half of a מנה,
maneh, half of a unit in the morning and half in the
afternoon of קטורת. Ketoret. Today there would obviously be the extra amount,
the double hand-breadths that would be done at this, you know, in
the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
Yes. I was just thinking before
about the sound, maybe there's an allusion here to הכל יפה לבשמים.
Hakol yafeh l'visamim. Okay. So which?
Oh, you mean the sounds of them about the? Yeah,
that normally is said when you're sort of grinding it, but maybe.
Okay, interesting association. Alright, okay.
Nice point. בכל יום, bechol yom, okay, בכל יום
היתה דקה.
bechol yom
hayta dakah.
Normally it would be thin,
fine, thank you, והיום דקה מן הדקה v'hayom dakah min hadakah today
it was ground extra fine. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, we taught דקה,
dakah, right? Because it says on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it says
that he shall bring קטורת דקה, ketoret dakah, fine incense. מה תלמוד
לומר? Mah talmud lomar? Why did it have to say fine incense?
והלא כבר נאמר ושחקת ממנה הדק vehalo kvar ne'emar v'shachakta mimenah hadek
when it talks about the regular incense it says grind it finely.
אלא להביא דקה מן הדקה ela l'havi dakah min hadakah to tell
you that you do an extra grinding and you make it extra
fine. בכל יום כהנים עולים במזרחו של כבש. bechol yom kohanim olim
bemizrachu shel kevesh.
Normally the כהנים kohanim would go up on the east, circle counter-clockwise,
come down on the west. And today, now again, let's take a
look. דאמר מר כל פינות שאתה פונה לא יהו אלא דרך ימין
למזרח. d'amar mar kol pinot she'atah poneh lo yehu ela derech yamin
l'mizrach. All the turnings you do should be towards your east and
if you're coming up on the ramp on the south then when
you turn east, you are turning, when you turn to your, I'm
sorry, to turn to your right. All turnings you do should be
towards your right and if you're coming up on the ramp on
the south, then a move to the right means to turn east
and to go counter-clockwise.
But you're still, you're always facing, you're trying, you're really trying to
walk on the side sort of and
you're facing a bit turning? No, no, you imagine the continued turning
is as if you're pointing towards the center. It doesn't mean that
as you're walking you're pointing towards the center. But once your initial
move is towards the east, then obviously your circuit is going to
be a counter-clockwise circuit. Okay, והיום, v'hayom,
now here again is the question of the very fascinating two גרסאות.
girsaot. רש"י's Rashi's גרסא girsa is עולה באמצע ויורד באמצע. oleh b'emtza
v'yored b'emtza. There's just the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and he can
go up in the middle and come down in the middle. מה
טעמא, Mah ta'ama, what's the reason? משום כבודו של כהן גדול. mishum
kevodo shel Kohen Gadol.
It's his honor like we're making the, we just commented yet this
morning, like that ad for the lottery, you know, you have your
own lane through traffic and through the toll booth and everything. You
get to come straight in the middle, nobody else is around. But
a fascinating גרסא girsa is not עולה oleh but עולים באמצע ויורדים
באמצע. olim b'emtza v'yordim b'emtza. That there were other, the כהנים kohanim
were also there. They weren't doing the עבודה, avodah, but when the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol went up, first you would have a whole
retinue of כהנים kohanim going up in front of him, you know,
I don't know who it would be, but you'd have a whole
retinue going up in front of him in the middle and then
coming down, you know, in front of him when he would come
down. So that would really like, you know, show the importance that
actually seems like that would add a lot to you know the
excitement of what was happening and focus you on the importance of
what was happening. You know otherwise it seems like very, I don't
know, almost like quiet or lonely, I mean I guess you know
there is that whole sense. of יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*
obviously, אהרן *Aaron* enters into the קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*, there is
that whole sense of like this intimacy, you know, and the privacy
and just the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, and certainly just
the כהן kohen, גדול *Kohen Gadol* enters into the קודש קדשים *Kodesh
Kodashim*. But if you think about it from the perspective of everybody
that's around watching, you know, having one guy run here and one
here and one there, and like maybe a slight assist to like
שחיטה shechita, *shechting* or mixing the blood, you know, you don't get
that sense of like not just excitement, but of like of weight,
of significance, of like of, you know, even of, you know, majesty,
thank you. You know, so the idea I think it changes your
sense of what was happening to thinking that there was a lot
of people that were around him that were doing things to add
to the sense of the moment and the weight of what was
happening.
Maybe even a hazard a guess to say the same people we
mentioned in the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara*, the פרק *Perek*, the סגן *Sgan* we know, ראש בית אב
*Rosh Beit Av*, משלו *mishelo*, and the several כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* that
would be there. Could be, but I think it's more exciting to
think that there were 20 כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* that ran up the
the, you know, the כבש kevesh? *Kevesh* in front of him. Right.
Okay, בכל יום *Bechol yom*,
but it just mentions כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*, normally כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* would
go this way, today the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* would go, you know,
up the the middle.
The people who had like
their משמר *mishmar* that day? I good, yeah, I don't know. מאי
*Mai*, okay, so בכל יום היה ארבע מערכות *Bechol yom hayah arba
ma'arachot*. Now we get to, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. בכל
יום כהן Kohen, גדול מקדש Mikdash. ידיו ורגליו מן הכיור *Bechol yom
Kohen Gadol mekadesh yadav v'raglav min hakyiyor*, normally he would wash from
the general laver that everybody else would use, today from a special,
you know, pitcher on his of, for a private pitcher. מאי טעמא
משום כבודו של כהן Kohen גדול *Mai ta'ama mishum kvodo shel Kohen
Gadol* for his honor. It's interesting to give that reason because I
would have said here, more than the honor, would be the issue
of the חולשה *chulsha*, he's up there, he's going to the מקווה
*mikvah*, he's going to do a washing, you know, before the מקווה
*mikvah*, washing after the מקווה *mikvah*, what he's supposed to run down
and wash his hands, go to the מקווה *mikvah*, run down wash
his hands? So it's interesting that here it gives the reason of
כבודו *kvodo*. But of course there was the opinion in the משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* that every day he would have his private, you know,
pitcher to wash his hands and that certainly would be כבודו של
כהן Kohen, גדול *kvodo shel Kohen Gadol*. בכל יום היה ארבע מערכות
*Bechol yom hayah arba ma'arachot*. Now we get to the number of
fires, pyres on the top of the altar. And so everybody agrees
that one was added for the קטורת ktoret *ketoret*, the coals for
the קטורת ktoret *ketoret* that was burnt on the, in the Holy
of Holies. The question was what was the standard number? And to
remind you, the opinions in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* of the standard
number was four, three, and two. Right? The משנה *Mishnah* said, normally
it would be four, today five, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi
Meir*. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose *Rabbi Yossi* says normally three. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says normally two. So let's take a look
what that's based on. תנו רבנן Rabbanan, *Tanu rabanan*, so our rabbis
taught. בכל יום היו שתים מערכות *Bechol yom hayu shtayim ma'arachot*, normally
there would just be two pyres, that would be the position of,
I forget already, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose *Rabbi Yossi*, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. Okay, והיום שלוש *v'hayom shalosh*,
and today three. אחת מערכה גדולה *Achat ma'aracha gedolah*, so what would
be the standard two? One would be the main pyre where you
would be burning the limbs and the fats of the sacrifice. ואחת
מערכה שנייה *V'achat ma'aracha shniya*, and the other a secondary fire, what
would that be for? של קטורת ketoret *shel ketoret*, the normal קטורת
ketoret? *ketoret* that you would do on the gold altar twice a
day. That would be your normal. Okay, ואחת שמוסיפין בו bo ביום
*v'achat shemosifin bo bayom*, and an extra one specifically for today for
the, for the coals that you would be using for the, for
the incense of the Holy of Holies.
Instead of taking the one from the קטורת ketoret *ketoret*.
Yeah, so we're going to discuss why everybody agrees there was an
extra one today. We're going to discuss where these different ones come
from and why it's agreed that there was an extra one today.
דברי רבי יהודה divrei Rabbi Yehuda. *Divrei Rabbi Yehuda*, that's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* said. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose אומר בכל
יום שלוש *Rabbi Yossi omer bechol yom shalosh*, normally three, והיום ארבע
*v'hayom arba*. What was the three? אחת של מערכה גדולה *Achat shel
ma'aracha gedolah*, one for the main one, we got that. ואחת מערכה
שנייה של קטורת ketoret *v'achat ma'aracha shniya shel ketoret*, a minor one,
a secondary one for the incense, for the coals for the incense,
the regular incense. ואחת של קיום האש kiyum ha'esh. *v'achat shel kiyum
ha'esh*, and another one for maintaining the fire. I'll get back to
what that means in a minute, אש תמיד esh tamid *esh tamid*,
right. אש תמיד esh tamid *esh tamid*, hold on. ואחת שמוסיפין בו
ביום *v'achat shemosifin bo bayom*, and one extra. So what does it
mean for maintaining the fire? So Michael is correct and we're going
to look in a minute in terms of the verse, but obviously
he was, it's based reflecting the verse of אש תמיד תוקד על
המזבח eish tamid tukad al hamizbeach. *esh tamid tukad al hamizbe'ach*. Now
if I told you there was a third one for maintaining the
fire, I have to tell you, my assumption would have been that
what it means is you're going to have one sort of, it's
sort of like the נר תמיד ner tamid, *ner tamid*. You're going
to have one fire that its whole purpose is that it should
always be burning. Not just functionally you're burning the limbs, you're doing
this, obviously you're going to try to maintain that it's got going,
but if you're in the middle of burning limbs and burning whatever,
you know, and it's a big fire, who knows, maybe sometime it
goes out, but there's this other fire that you're constantly making sure
is always burning, that's its whole purpose. That's what I imagined, like
a נר תמיד tamid *ner tamid*. But you look at רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* where it says קיום האש kiyum ha-esh. *kiyum ha'esh*, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says where's the רש"י Rashi *Rashi*?
באמצע של גיונא שפיר *b'emtza shel giyuna hashap*,
thank you.
קיום האש kiyum ha-esh, *kiyum ha'esh*, ובה עשר שורות למטה בתוך השורות
*v'bah eser shurot lemata betoch hashurot*, first word on the line, maybe
12 lines, שאם אין אש eish. של מערכה גדולה מתגבר mitgaber מוסיפין
עליו מזה *she'im ein esh shel ma'aracha gedolah mitgaber mosifin alav mizeh*.
So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says no, what this meant is to be
מקיים *mekayeim* the אש esh *esh* of the main fire, that if
the main fire was going out you could just grab some fire
here. Now of course the first thing I would do if the
fire is going out is grab some kindling and some wood. Why
exactly you need a fire, you know, okay, because you know if
your fire's going out, you know. Not that it goes down. So
מתגבר has to be bigger than the smaller one. No, I didn't
think it's no, מתגבר I just think it
means it's not roaring.
I disagree. It's not a roaring fire.
If you've got one
big and one small, this one's got to
be the big daddy. No,
no. I don't think that. The way I'm reading רש"י is the
purpose is to make sure that the main fire is always going
out and if it's not a roaring fire and you're concerned it's
going out, you want to make sure that you have this to
feed it. Okay. We will have to agree to disagree on this
though. All right, fine. So now back to the גמרא. Gemara So
that's according to him an extra one for קיום האש. kiyum ha-esh.
Where were we? Okay. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi omer בכל יום שלוש
והיום ארבע, bechol yom shalosh, ve'hayom arba,
we just did that. Okay. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so if you
take a look מאיר Meir starts the line, it's in parentheses with
an asterisk. On the side it says בתוספתא ליתא. betosefta lesa. So
obviously in our משנה this is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir? but in
the תוספתא Tosefta it's a non-it's רבי. Rebbi. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer,
so it's interesting, is it רבי Rebbi or רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir,
Not a big חק chak because you know סתם משנה's stam mishna
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir so רבי Rebbi who is the editor of
the משנה might have adopted רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. So רבי
Rebbi or רבי מאיר Rabbi Mayer. omer בכל יום ארבע bechol yom
arba normally four והיום חמש ve'hayom chamish and today five. So what
are the four? אחת שמערכה גדולה achas shema'aracha gedola the big one,
אחת שמערכה שניה של קטורת achas shema'aracha shniya shel ketores the smaller
one which is used for the gold altar for the daily incense,
ואחת לקיום האש ve'achas lekiyum ha'esh
the third one for maintaining a constant fire, ואחת לאיברים ופדרים שלא
נתאכלו מבערב. ve'achas le'eivarim upedarim shelo nit'aklu miba'erev.
The fourth one is, yes, on the main fire you would burn
the limbs and the fats. But that would be where you would
put the limbs and the fats that were brought that day. Come
the next morning, if they had not been totally consumed, so where
do you do? So the normal sense would be leave them there
or if they fall off of the main wood, you put them
back up. No, according to him, the idea was that was for
the day sacrifices of the day. Makes sense. It's like my kids.
Leftovers?
We don't want leftovers. So you want that to focus on the
sacrifices of the day. Things that still have to get done that
weren't taken care of yesterday, they get done offline, they get done
on a separate wood pile. מזבח. mizbeach.
That's what he said.
All right, so that gives you four normally.
To me every night then, that's what- every morning, no,
because
the קרבנות korbanot of the day would burn through the night and
the goal was to have them burned through the night. So every
morning if something had not finished burning on the main wood- on
the main fire, you would move it to the secondary fire and
you leave the main fire for- מבערב miba'erev
means the whole night.
Right. From the night before, that had not been consumed the night
before. ואחת שמוסיפין בכל יום. ve'achas shemosifin bechol yom. דכולי עלמא מיהת
de'chulay alma mi'at
everybody agrees, תרתי איתא tartei issa everybody agrees that there's a minimum
of two, and everybody also agrees you add one for today. So
let's see first where you get the debates in terms of the
number. Everybody agrees there was a minimum of two. מנלן menalan where
do you know it? You read the תורה Torah it sounds like
there was just one fire, right? The beginning of צו Tzav is
all about the fire, אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח. esh tamid tukad
al hamizbeach Where do you get the idea of multiple fires? So
אמר קרא amar kra the verse says, so let's actually read the
פסוק pasuk to orient ourselves. היא העולה
על מוקדה על המזבח כל הלילה עד הבוקר ואש המזבח תוקד בו.
hi ha'ola
al mokda al hamizbeach kol halaila ad haboker ve'eish hamizbeach tukad bo.
So first you have the העולה ha'ola is on מוקדה mokda the
fire, the pyre, ואש המזבח תוקד בו ve'eish hamizbeach tukad bo again
מוקדה mokda תוקד tukad right?
And the fire burns in it, that's another mention of a fire.
ולבש הכהן vilavash hakohen etc. אשר תאכל האש את העולה על המזבח.
asher tochal ha'esh et ha'ola al hamizbeach.
So it mentions the fire. ולבש הכהן מדו בד ומכנסי בד ילבש
על בשרו והרים את הדשן אשר תאכל האש את העולה על המזבח
ושמו אצל המזבח. vilavash hakohen mido bad umichnesei bad yilbash al besaro
veherim et hadeshen asher tochal ha'esh et ha'ola al hamizbeach vesamo etzel
hamizbeach. So a third mention, the fire that consumed the העולה. ha'ola.
And then it says והאש על המזבח תוקד בו לא תכבה וביער
עליה הכהן עצים בבקר בבקר. ve'ha'esh al hamizbeach tukad bo lo tichbe
uvi'er alei hakohen etzim baboker baboker. אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח לא
תכבה. eish tamid tukad al hamizbeach lo tichbe.
So there seems like a little redundancy here and five separate mentions
of either a מוקדה mokda or an אש. esh So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara does with it.
וביער עליה הכהן עצים בבקר בבקר וסידר שני גזירי
עצים.
uvi'er alei hakohen etzim baboker baboker ve'sidar
shenei gizrei etzim.
Right. Okay, so היא העולה על מוקדה hi ha'ola al mokda that
is the first one, it is the העולה ha'ola on the pyre
על המזבח כל הלילה. al hamizbeach kol halaila. זו מערכה גדולה zu
ma'aracha gedola
this is the main one. ואש המזבח תוקד בו ve'eish hamizbeach tukad
bo and then it says another, the fire burns in it, that's
a little redundant. זו מערכה שניה של קטורת zu ma'aracha shniya shel
ketores
that's the second one. That's how just in the opening פסוק pasuk
of that section, everybody agrees that you get two fires. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi
let's see, רבי יוסי קיום האש מנא ליה? Rebbi Yose kiyum ha'esh
menaleh?
So where does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi get a third one, the
one that's done for the sake of sustaining the fire? נפקא ליה
nafka lei מ"והאש על המזבח תוקד בו" mive'ha'esh al hamizbeach tukad bo
והאש ve'ha'esh
the extra
ו"ה vav hey I believe is the דרשה. drasha. No, I'm sorry,
the next פסוק. pasuk. No, no, that's later. The next פסוק. pasuk.
First it says... והאש על המזבח תוקד בו ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad
bo in פסוק ב, pasuk bet, and then פסוק ה pasuk hei
is והאש על המזבח תוקד בו לא תכבה. ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad
bo lo tikhbe. So again, we have yet another mention of a
fire. והאש על המזבח תוקד בו. ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo. So
that's where he gets a third one. ורבי יהודה ve-Rabbi Yehuda now
what does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say back who doesn't believe that
there's a third one? ההיא לאצצות אליסתא הוא דאתא. hahi le-atzatzos alista
hu de-ata.
That's for lighting the like kindling. What does that mean? דתניא, de-tanya,
we learn in a ברייתא. braita. היה רבי יהודה אומר, hayah Rabbi
Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say: מניין לאצצות אליסתא, minayin
le-atzatzos alista,
how do you know for the lighting of the kindling שלא תהא
אלא בראשו של מזבח, she-lo tehei ela be-rosho shel mizbe'ach, that you
can't sort of strike a match, light your kindling at the bottom
and then bring it up the altar? How do you know you
do the actual lighting at the top of the altar? תלמוד לומר
והאש על המזבח תוקד בו, talmud lomar ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo,
the fire should be burnt on it, meaning when you are lighting
a fire to for kindling to add to the main main pyre,
you must do it בו on the top of the altar. Okay,
that is no, that's not קיום האש. kiyum ha-esh This is why
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, does not believe that there's a third one.
Right, so everybody's opening פסוק pasuk mentions two fires, everybody uses two.
Then towards the end of the paragraph it again says והאש על
המזבח תוקד בו. ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo. So רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi says that is coming to teach you a third fire for
קיום האש, kiyum ha'esh. תוקד בו לא תכבה, tukad bo lo tikhbe,
it must never go out, right? That emphasizes constant. That's the third
one for the קיום האש. kiyum ha-esh, And רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda,
says no, that means when you're lighting wood at the you know
for the sake of keeping the fire, not you have a separate
pyre, make sure you do it תוקד בו tukad bo on the
top of the altar. Even if you got the wood from the
storehouse? Yeah, wherever you get the kindling from, exactly. Okay, so that
third reference is a question: is it קיום האש or is it
talking about lighting kindling and it must be done at the top
of the altar? Okay, תלמוד לומר תוקד בו. talmud lomar tukad bo.
אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosi, מניין שעושה מערכה לקיום
האש? minayin she-oseh ma'arakhah le-kiyum ha-esh? Now we're going to get רבי
יוסי to have the floor. How do I know that you have
a separate fire for the sake of sustaining the fire? תלמוד לומר
והאש על המזבח תוקד בו, talmud lomar ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo,
quoting the verse, the second time it mentions at the end of
the paragraph והאש על המזבח תוקד בו, ve-ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo,
the third mention of a fire, that I get the idea he
says that there's a third fire for sustaining it. רבי יוסי אצצות
אליסתא מנא ליה? Rabbi Yosi atzatzos alista mena lei? How does he
know according to how does רבי יוסי know
this idea that when you want to light kindling you have to
do it at the top of the altar, since for him this
verse is talking about a third fire? Where does he get that
other idea from? נפקא ליה מהיכא דנפקא ליה לרבי שמעון. nafka lei
me-heikha de-nafka lei le-Rabbi Shimon. He gets it from where רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon gets it. דתניא, de-tanya, we learn in the ברייתא: braita:
ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח. ve-nasnu benei Aharon ha-kohen esh
al ha-mizbe'ach. This is not in צו, Tzav, but in the beginning
of ויקרא. Vayikra. By the way, the basic difference I think I've
mentioned this before, but since we're looking at the פסוקים psukim I
should mention it you know, צו Tzav and ויקרא Vayikra seem like
repeats. So ויקרא Vayikra goes through all the קרבנות, korbanos, and then
צו Tzav seems to like go through the same קרבנות korbanos again.
The difference is that ויקרא Vayikra is from the perspective of the
person bringing the קרבן, korban, right? ויקרא Vayikra is אדם כי יקריב
מכם קרבן. adam ki yakriv mikem korban. צו Tzav is from the
perspective of the כהנים. Kohanim צו את אהרן ואת בניו לאמר זאת
תורת העלה. tzav es Aharon ve-es banav lemor zos toras ha-olah. So
by by צו, Tzav, if it focuses on the on the on
the כהנים, Kohanim,
they got to do a lot in terms of maintaining the fire
and getting the ashes off, right? That's a lot of the focus
of the כהנים. Kohanim. So you mention an עולה, olah, but the
whole focus of the first paragraph on צו Tzav is majorly about
the fire, whereas the first paragraph and the focus of ויקרא Vayikra
is about an עולה olah and the fire is only incidental, right?
דבר אל בני ישראל, daber el benei Yisrael, not צו את אהרן.
tzav es Aharon. ואמרת אליהם אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן מן הבהמה,
ve-amarta aleihem adam ki yakriv mikem korban min ha-behemah, what animal do
you bring
it from? מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן. min ha-behemah min ha-bakar
u-min ha-tzon. אם עלה קרבנו מן הבקר זכר תמים אל פתח אהל
מועד יקריב אתו, im olah korbano min ha-bakar zakhar tamim el pesach
ohel mo'ed yakriv oso, he should bring it, וסמך ידו, ve-samakh yado,
it's all about the way he brings it. And then at the
end it says ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח וערכו עצים
על האש. ve-nasnu benei Aharon ha-kohen esh al ha-mizbe'ach ve-arkhu etzim al
ha-esh. It mentions the fire parenthetically, but this is from the perspective
of the person bringing it; that is of less interest to him.
So that's the basic difference between the opening of ויקרא Vayikra and
the opening of צו. Tzav. So now one minute, with that in
mind let's just see. רבי יוסי so where does he get this
idea of lighting the kindling at the top of the altar? He
gets it from ויקרא. Vayikra. The צו Tzav פסוקים, psukim, the extra
mention of fire is for a third fire. This idea of lighting
the kindling at the top, that's from ויקרא. Vayikra. דנפקא ליה לרבי
שמעון דתניא ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח. de-nafka lei le-Rabbi
Shimon de-tanya ve-nasnu benei Aharon ha-kohen esh al ha-mizbe'ach. לימד limed
so from ויקרא Vayikra they should put the wood on the fire
לימד על אצצות אליסתא שלא תהא אלא בכהן כשר. limed al atzatzos
alista she-lo tehei ela be-kohen kasher. It has to be בני אהרן,
benei Aharon, so it only has to be when they are it
has to be, you know, in their full status of a כהן,
Kohen. a כהן כשר. kohen kasher. ובכלי שרת, u-ve-khli sharet,
and wearing the you know if they're if they're putting wood on
it, they have to use the holy vessels; they themselves have to
be dressed in the garments. דברי רבי יהודה.
Rabi Yehuda Could be used to put wood on...
Whatever, you know, I don't know, shovels and other types of things.
That's what רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda, says. So רבי יהודה, Rabi Yehuda
who learned the kindling from the פסוק pasuk in צו, Tzav, this
extra פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra where it speaks about בני אהרן,
benei Aharon, he says that's not about lighting the kindling at the
top of the altar, that's talking about who does it. It has
to be done only by כהנים Kohanim, and כלי שרת. kli sharet.
אמר לו רבי שמעון, amar lo Rabbi Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon said back to him: וכי תעלה על דעתך שזר קרב לגבי
מזבח? ve-khi ta'aleh al da'atkha she-zar karev legabe mizbe'ach?
You need a פסוק pasuk to tell you that a non-כהן, Kohen?
that only כהנים Kohanim. can do it? How could you even begin
to think that a non-כהן Kohen could go up on the altar,
which is quite fascinating. We have before, we have had before
the whole idea of שחיטה, shechita right, is כשרה ksheira with a
non-כהן, Kohen maybe even the שחיטה of the כהן Kohen גדול's פר
par on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So you could be doing something
that's obviously a significant עבודה, avoda, doing it there on the floor
of the עזרה, Azara, but nevertheless the whole going up to the
altar for רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon is patently obvious that that would
be completely off-limits to a non-כהן. Kohen, It's quite fascinating, you know,
no פסוק, pasuk, no anything, yes we know כהנים Kohanim, could do
other things, but to go up on the מזבח mizbeach you would
not need a פסוק. pasuk. That's obvious, and it's very interesting, תוספות
Tosafot deals with it elsewhere, you know, here and elsewhere like, you
know, this idea about how much could you just from this intuitive
idea automatically make certain assumptions and rule out like, you know, what
the verse, you know, what you need the verse to be teaching
you about who does what in the מקדש. mikdash? So he says
you cannot, you do not need that verse to tell you only
כהנים, Kohanim if it's on the מזבח, mizbeach, then clearly it's only
כהנים. So what does he do with that verse? So, אלא לימד
על הצתת אליתא, ella limed al hatzatat alita,
what the verse is telling you is not that you need כהנים,
it's telling you that when you light the kindling שלא תהא אלא
בראשו של מזבח, shelo tehei ella be'rosho shel mizbeach, that has to
be on the top of the altar. Once you know the kindling
is lit on the altar, then obviously it has to be כהנים.
So, but, so, so I don't need a verse to teach me
כהנים, I need the verse to teach me you gotta do it
at the top of the altar. Once I know that, the need
of כהנים is taken for
granted.
You had a question, David?
Yes,
so
I
find it
interesting because it
maybe answers my
question, when they say
it
has to
have
a
כהן כשר Kohen kasher and
כלי שרת, klei shareit, like what
כלי שרת klei shareit do you need to
bring a
log of
wood?
רש"י says בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Right, an interesting
way of saying בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna.
I know, so I mentioned בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, but it could
also be referring to things that you're also doing, like I said,
if you're just, you know, who knows and you know you're moving
things around, you have pitchforks. Okay, let's go on. Okay,
so רבי יהודה, now what would רבי יהודה say back? רבי יהודה,
you know, רבי יהודה might say it's not obvious that a זר
zar can't go on the altar, but the גמרא Gemara thinks that
maybe he if he does agree to that, so why does he
need one פסוק pasuk to tell me the top of the altar
and one פסוק pasuk to tell me only a כהן? Kohen No,
if you just told me the idea of, what do you call
it, of top of the altar, I still have got a non-כהן
kohen. in. How could you have got a non-כהן in if you
agree that no non-כהן is going on the altar? הוה אמינא, hava
amina, I would have said קיימא ארעא ועביד במפוחא. kaia ar'a v'avid
be'mapucha. You could be on the ground and use a, what are
those things called? A bellows. A bellows, a bellows. Now it's gotta
be a pretty big bellows that's like thirty-two אמות amot high or
whatever, and then you know you gotta get it at an angle,
anyway, but the point is yes, the lighting of the flame had
to be on the top of the מזבח, mizbeach, that obviously I
agree with you, the גמרא Gemara saying, would have to be with
a כהן, but I might think that a non-כהן could. could do
something from the floor and therefore it has to tell me that
any any addition to the fire, any tending to the fire, wherever
you're standing has to be a כהן. Okay. רבי מאיר. Rabbi Mayer
Okay, so that's our first debate, our first issue of number three
for the קיום האש. Do you learn it from the extra mention
of אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח Esh tamid tukad al hamizbe'ach at
the end of the paragraph in צו, Tzav, or is that telling
me about lighting the kindling? Now, how about רבי מאיר Rabbi Mayer
that gets a fourth one? רבי מאיר Rabbi Mayer. איברים ופדרים שלא
נתאכלו מבעוד ערב מנלן? evarim u'fedarim shelo nis'achlu mibe'erev minalein? Where does
he get an idea that there is a fourth fire for transferring
the stuff that did not burn overnight, yesterday's קרבנות, korbanot, transferring them
to a fourth fire? Where does he get this fourth fire? נפקא
ליה מ והאש. nafkaleh mi-v'ha'esh. Okay, the והאש על המזבח תוקד בו
לא תכבה, v'ha'esh al hamizbeach tukad bo lo tichbe,
the extra ו. vav. ורבנן ו לא דרשי, v'Rabbanan vav lo darshi,
that ו vav they're not impressed by that. Okay, והאש. v'ha'esh. So
רבנן, איברים ופדרים שלא נתאכלו מבעוד ערב מה עביד להו? evarim u'fedarim
shelo nis'achlu mibe'erev ma avid lehu?
What are you doing with the limbs that did not get consumed
in the night? So the answer is pretty obvious. מהדר להו למערכה
גדולה. mahader lehu l'ma'arachah gedolah. Fine, you put it, you either you
keep them on the main fire, or if they fell off the
main fire you put them back on the main fire. So you
don't need a separate fire for that. דתניא, de-tanya, we've done a
ברייתא: brayta: מנלן לאיברים ופדרים שלא נתאכלו מבעוד ערב, minalein l'evarim u'fedarim
shelo nis'achlu mibe'erev, how do you know the limbs that did not
get consumed the night before, שסדרן על גבי מזבח, she-sodran al gabei
mizbeach,
that you put them, you sort of
arrange them on the top of the altar, meaning because you're going
to come in in the morning and you might have to fix
the main fire, right, you know, sweep out the dust and rearrange
it and put on logs, and you don't want to necessarily be
dealing with all the limbs that are there. So or limbs that
fell off for the fire and are on the top of the
altar but not on the fire. So you take all the limbs,
you move them to a side, you put them at the top
of the altar, you fix your fire and then you're going to
put them back on the fire. Okay, ואם אין מחזיקין, v'im ein
machzikin,
and if there's not enough space at the top of the altar
for those limbs, שסדרן על הכבש, she-sodran al ha-kevesh, you put them
on the ramp, או על גבי סובב, o al gabei sovev, or
on the walk-around, עד שיעשה מערכה גדולה, ad she-ya'aseh ma'arachah gedolah, until
you can fix the main fire, ויחזירן, v'yachziran, and then put them
back on the main fire. תלמוד לומר אשר תאכל האש את העולה
על המזבח, Talmud lomar asher tochal ha'esh et ha'olah al hamizbeach,
that the fire consumes the עולה olah on the altar. So the
extra פסוק pasuk of אשר תאכל האש את העולה על המזבח, asher
tochal ha'esh et ha'olah al hamizbeach, the extra mention is according to
this that you not that you have an additional fire, but it's
the same fire that you're going to use to be תאכל העולה,
tochal ha'olah, to finish consuming the עולה olah and to finish consuming
anything else. What?
Put on the floor? Of the כבש? kevesh What? Put on the
floor.
No, on the ramp, not on the floor. כבש kevesh.
is a ramp.
Yes, on the floor of the כבש. kevesh Right, but not the
floor of the עזרה. Azarah. Yeah. Right.
כבש is also made out of marble? Slippery. Stone, yes, marble,
stone, yeah. It's slippery. I
don't know, it's a good question. Okay, so one minute. Okay. דאי...
de-ee... okay, so רבי מאיר. Rabbi Mayer Now
רבי מאיר Rabbi Mayer who says that there's a separate fire, why
do I need this extra phrase אשר תאכל האש את העולה? asher
tochal ha'esh et ha'olah? What do I do with that? To teach
me: איכולי עולה אתה מחזיר ואי אתה מחזיר איכולי קטורת, ichulei olah
atah machzir v'ee atah machzir ichulei ktoret, that you only restore it's
only things that you put back, whether you're putting back on the
main fire, whether you're putting back on a secondary fire, רבי מאיר
says I think
there's an extra fire, what do I do with this emphasis of
אשר תאכל האש את העולה asher tochal ha'esh et ha'olah which the
rabbis say means use the same fire, the same fire that burned
the עולה? olah? I don't emphasize same fire, I emphasize עולה. olah.
Only animal parts, עולה olah which includes not only the עולה olah
but all animal sacrifices, do you put back. But if קטורת ketoret,
fell off of the gold altar, was burning in the gold altar
and a piece of קטורת ketoret. did not get consumed, you do
not put it back on
and
let it
burn. Okay, ואי אתה
מחזיר איכולי קטורת. v'ee atah machzir ichulei ktoret. Okay, דכולי עלמא מיהא,
de-kulei alma miha,
everybody
whatever
nevertheless agrees, מוסיפין בו ביום, mosifin bo bayom, they agree that there's
an extra fire for the day of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. מנלן,
minalein, where do they get it from? נפקא להו מ nafkalehu mi
והאש. v'haEsh. Like before we tried to do an extra vav, ואש,
v'esh, but there's a והאש. v'haEsh. Like it could have just said
אש המזבח תוקד בו. Esh hamizbe'ach tukad bo. What's the והאש v'haEsh
and the so that's coming to tell me that there are times
where there's even yet another fire. Right, exactly.
ואפילו למאן דלא
דריש ו,
v'afilu l'man d'la
darish
vav,
even if you're not normally impressed with an extra vav, ו"ה דריש,
vav-he darish, an extra vav and a he is clearly extra and
therefore coming to tell you that there's going to be sometimes yet
another fire. Again, the funny thing is is that all the other
fires are on a daily basis. This one is for one day
out of the year. There's nothing that links this hint in the
פסוק pasuk to you know to any specifically to יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur.
Yeah, but just everything else what do you need it like on
a day there's a lot of קרבנות. korbanos. Yeah, anyway.
Okay. Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this, אש תמיד esh tamid
now we've interpreted the whole פסוק pasuk except the last one. אש
תמיד תוקד על המזבח לא תכבה. Esh tamid tukad al hamizbe'ach lo
sichbeh. If there was any verse that you would say would be
this idea of a third fire for קיום האש, it would be
that last פסוק pasuk in the paragraph. What do we do with
that? We've completely ignored that. So אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח לא
תכבה, Esh tamid tukad al hamizbe'ach lo sichbeh, what do you do
with that? אש תמיד למאי אתא? Esh tamid l'mai ata? מבעי ליה
לכדתניא mib'ei lei l'khid'tanya for what we taught in the ברייתא, Braisa,
אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח לא תכבה, Esh tamid tukad al hamizbe'ach
lo sichbeh, לימד limed it
teaches you המערכה שניה של קטורת ha-ma'aracha shniya shel ketoret that you
have to have a separate fire for the feeding the what do
you call for using the קטורת ketoret for putting on the gold
altar on a daily basis. But maybe it didn't have to be
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. How do you know it has to be
kept on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Because the פסוק pasuk we learned it
out from was what was it?
Where else would you put it?
Well, maybe you would burn it on the מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav.
Maybe you would maintain, you'd maintain a fire on the מזבח הזהב.
mizbe'ach hazahav. So what? How much do you need to burn the
קטורת? ketoret Okay. והאש על המזבח
תוקד בו.
v'ha-esh al
ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo. Yeah,
so
I don't exactly get it cause the פסוק pasuk does say והאש
על המזבח תוקד בו. v'ha-esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo. So תוקד בו
tukad bo presumably on the altar,
but maybe I would have said it meant the golden altar. How
do I know that I make the fire for the golden altar
for the קטורת ketoret. on the outer altar? Maybe I make it
on the gold altar? So that's what the פסוק pasuk of אש
esh תמיד tamid תוקד על המזבח is telling you, somehow the repetition,
again I don't know how you know which altar, is underscoring the
outer altar.
Just for יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur No, every day they would take fire, remember we said
on a daily basis they would take coals from the top of
the מזבח mizbe'ach and bring it in? Every single day when they
had to burn the קטורת ketoret. on the golden altar, they'd go
up here, they'd get from the second pile which was for the
קטורת, ketoret, they'd go in here, they'd put it on the top
of the altar and they'd put on the קטורת. ketoret, Today, they
would have a third pile, an additional one for the coals they're
going to be using for in here. The question is you have
all these פסוקים psukim about fire, fire, fire, and all the fires
are on here, but maybe the פסוק pasuk that tells you about
a fire for the קטורת ketoret is not, it's telling you you
keep a fire on that altar, you maintain a fire on that
altar. How do you know that the fire for the קטורת ketoret,
is what you do here and then you take the coals and
bring them in? So that we are learning from this extra פסוק.
pasuk. Okay, but this is on a daily basis. Okay. לימד על
מערכה שניה של קטורת, Limed al ma'aracha shniya shel ketoret, the second
one they had the daily one, שלא תהא אלא על מזבח החיצון
she-lo tehei ela al mizbe'ach hachitzon that it is only on the
outer altar. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara's says like this, אש מחתה ומנורה מנין? Esh
machtah u'menorah minayin?
So the fire for the מחתה machtah of יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
and the light that you would use for the מנורה, menorah, how
do you know that you would get that from the outer altar?
Right, we've learned all these fires, we've learned that the fire for
this comes from the outer altar, how do you know that the
fire, we learned that there was an idea of a fifth fire,
extra fire for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur but it's not so clear
that it's on the outer altar. How do you know the fire
you would use for יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the fire you
would use for the מנורה, menorah, right,
that also was taken from the fire on the top of the
outer altar? Where do you get that from? So אש מחתה, esh
machtah, there's one of three things, it's two things, אש מחתה, esh
machtah, the fire of the fire pan for יום כיפור Yom Kippur?
ומנורה מנין, u'menorah minayin,
how do you know that those also come from the, since we
said the one for the gold altar comes from it, how do
you know those come from the outer altar? ודינו, V'dinu, it's you
can learn it out logically. נאמר אש בקטורת ונאמר אש במחתה. Ne'emar
esh b'ketoret v'ne'emar esh b'machtah.
It says fire by the burning of incense and it says fire
by the מחתה, machtah, right,
ולקח מעל המזבח גחלי אש. v'lakach mei-al ha-mizbe'ach gachalei esh. Now, by
the way,
ומנורה, u'menorah, and it says it by מנורה, menorah, right? It says
בהעלותך את הנרות. be'haalotcha es ha-neirot.
Anyway,
it says אש esh somewhere by מנורה. menorah. The problem is is
that it doesn't say אש esh by קטורת. ketoret Right, it says
it by all three of them, but actually doesn't say אש esh
by קטורת. If you look at רש"י where רש"י says נאמר כאן
אש בקטורת דכתיב יקטירנה ואין הקטורת בלא אש. ne'emar kan esh b'ketoret
d'ichtiv yaktirenah v'ein ha-ketoret b'lo esh.
So that was a little bit of a cheat. Right, it says
oh, it says in אש esh all three times so we're going
to link them, but it doesn't say אש esh by the קטורת,
it just says יקטירנה yaktirenah and אש esh is inherent. So תוספות
Tosafot points out, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, נאמר אש בקטורת,
ne'emar esh biketoret, נראה לי דכתיב גבי קרח אתה ואהרן איש מחתתו
ותנו בהן אש ושימו עליהם קטורת. nir'eh li dechtiv gabei Korach atah
ve'Aharon ish machtato utnu bahen esh vesimu aleihem ketoret. Okay,
so you have אש esh linked to the קטורת, אש esh. by
the burning by the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, גחלי אש מעל המזבח,
gachalei esh me'al hamizbeach, okay, and you have the and you have
the אש esh by the מנורה. menorah. So and we're going to
link them. So it says like this, where were we? נאמר אש
בקטורת נאמר אש במחתה ומנורה, ne'emar esh biketoret ne'emar esh bemachta umenorah,
מה להלן על מזבח החיצון אף כאן על מזבח החיצון. mah lehalan
al mizbeach hachitzon af kan al mizbeach hachitzon.
The same way we learned that the אש esh for the daily
קטורת is from the outer altar, here too it's from the outer
altar. So by it's all linked by אש. esh That's one argument.
או כלך לדרך זו, o kelach lederech zu, or make the opposite
argument. נאמר אש בקטורת ונאמר אש במחתה ומנורה. ne'emar esh biketoret vene'emar
esh bemachta umenorah. So it says אש esh by all three. מה
להלן בסמוך לו אף מחתה ומנורה בסמוך
לו. mah lehalan besamuch lo af machta umenorah besamuch lo. Yes, they're
all in one group. Maybe not all in one group to say
they come from the outer altar, maybe all in one group to
say it comes from the closest source. So when you are here
and you need the fire for the burning of the regular קטורת,
the closest source of fire is here. But when you're going to
want to light the מנורה menorah or burn fire in the or
burn the incense in the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, what's the closest
source of fire? This one. This has already fire on it. So
yes, you learn that they're all similar, but all similar that they
all come from here, all similar that they come from the closest
source, and maybe both of those come from this one. Because you
know, you could have said what's the whole question? The פסוק pasuk
says, right, ולקח אהרן מעל המזבח גחלי אש. velakach Aharon me'al hamizbeach
gachalei esh. It says
מעל המזבח, me'al hamizbeach, but the question is which מזבח? mizbeach? Right?
Maybe he takes it from the gold altar. So how do we
know that it comes from the outer altar? Okay? אף מחתה ומנורה
בסמוך לו, af machta umenorah besamuch lo, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar אש
תמיד תוקד על המזבח לא תכבה. esh tamid tukad al hamizbeach lo
tichbeh.
Again, going back to that last פסוק, pasuk, אש esh תמיד tamid
to constantly burn on the altar. אש תמיד שאמרתי לך she'amarti lecha
the fire for the תמיד that I have said to you לא
תהא אלא בראשו של מזבח. lo tehei ela berosho shel mizbeach. So
what thing does it say תמיד about in the מקדש? נר תמיד,
right?
להעלות נר תמיד.
leha'alot ner tamid. So the fire for תמיד has to come from
the outer altar. That gets you מנורה. menorah. But now we're still
left with the question about the קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Okay? למדנו
אש ומנורה, lamadnu esh umenorah, that solved the idea that the מנורה's
menorah fire comes from the outer altar. אש למחתה מנין? esh lemachta
minayin? How about the fire for the fire pan for יום כיפור?
Maybe it comes still from the gold altar. בדין הוא, bedin hu,
let's again make the argument. נאמר אש במחתה ונאמר אש במנורה. ne'emar
esh bemachta vene'emar esh bemenorah. Let's just link those two, right? It
says אש by the מחתה machta and by the fire pan. It
says אש by the מנורה. menorah. מה להלן על גבי מזבח החיצון.
mah lehalan al gabei mizbeach hachitzon. We've now laid the basis for
saying the מנורה menorah comes from the outer altar, that's fire. אף
כאן על מזבח חיצון. af kan al mizbeach chitzon.
So the fire for the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is linked to
the מנורה menorah and therefore comes from the outer altar. או כלך
לדרך זו, o kelach lederech zu, or make the opposite argument. נאמר
אש בקטורת ונאמר אש במחתה. ne'emar esh biketoret vene'emar esh bemachta.
No, it says אש by the normal קטורת and it says אש
by the מחתה. machta. מה להלן בסמוך לו, mah lehalan besamuch lo,
the same type of argument. Maybe the point is not the outer
altar, the point is the most closest source of
fire. אף כאן בסמוך לו, af kan besamuch lo, and here too
maybe it comes from the closest source. Maybe you take the coals
from the מזבח mizbeach from the gold altar. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
ולקח מלא המחתה velakach melo hamachta finally the פסוק pasuk is in
אחרי מות, Acharei Mot, גחלי אש מעל המזבח gachalei esh me'al hamizbeach
and here's which מזבח? mizbeach? מלפני השם. milefinei Hashem. From the מזבח
mizbeach the great is from that part of the מזבח mizbeach that
is לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. איזהו מזבח שמקצתו לפני השם ואין כולו
לפני השם? eizehu mizbeach shemiktzato lifnei Hashem ve'ein kulo lifnei Hashem? Which
altar has a section which could be called close to God and
a section that's not directly close? הוי אומר זה מזבח החיצון. hevei
omer zeh mizbeach hachitzon. That is the outer one. Why? מלפני milefinei
because מלפני milefinei from the part that is לפני. lifnei. If you're
on the outer altar, you could say the stuff on the west
side is closer, is מלפני השם, milefinei Hashem, because it's closer to
the אולם ulam and the היכל heichal and so on, and the
stuff on the east side is further
away. So it's on this altar you can discuss what is מלפני
השם. milefinei Hashem. If it was this altar, it's already in the
presence of God, there's no section that is לפני השם lifnei Hashem
and not לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. So because of the verse of
מלפני milefinei of מלפני השם, milefinei Hashem, we learn that we're talking
about an altar that you can have a section that is closer
and further. We're talking about the outer altar, not the inner altar.
What?
You can't מלפני השם milefinei Hashem distinguish between the outer?
Yeah, you could have said no, maybe מזבח השם mizbeach Hashem just
means the one that is more in the presence of God. Yeah,
it's not. What? Can't לפני השם lifnei Hashem distinguish between the
altar? Yeah, you could've said no, maybe לפני השם lifnei Hashem דווקא
davka means the one that is more in the presence of God.
Yeah, that's not how the גמרא Gemara reading it is all I
can say. Why do I need וכפר? vechiper? If I have a
היקש hekesh I know that everything on the outside is like the
inside. So just like the inside requires four but works with one,
the outside should require four but work with one. So why do
I need וכפר? vechiper? To tell me that even if you only
did one מתנה matanah it works. But wait, I already know this
from a היקש. hekesh. The גמרא says we need וכפר vechiper for
the case of the חטאת chatas of the outer altar to say
that although you need four, it works with one. But I have
a היקש. hekesh. One is for the לכתחילה lechatchila and one is
for the בדיעבד. bedieved. One tells you you need four and the
other tells you that even if you only did one it works.
And we need the word וכפר vechiper by the inner חטאת chatas
and we need it by the outer חטאת chatas because I can't
learn one from the other. I might have thought that the inner
one which is more important needs all four for sure but the
outer one is okay with one. Or I might have thought that
the outer one which has more blood is okay with one but
the inner one is not. That's why the תורה Torah writes וכפר
vechiper by both of them.